Sméagol!
I've got one!
I've got a fish, Sméag. Sméagol!
Pull it in. Go on. Go on. Go on.
Pull it in.
Déagol.
Give us that, Déagol, my love.
Why?
Because...
it's my birthday and I wants it.
My precious.
They cursed us.
Murderer.
"Murderer" they called us.
They cursed us
and drove us away.
Gollum.
And we wept, precious.
We wept to be so alone.
And cool
So nice for feet
And we only wish
To catch a fish
So juicy sweet
And we forgot the taste of bread...
the sound of trees...
the softness of the wind.
We even forgot our own name.
My precious.
Wake up!
Wake up, sleepies.
We must go, yes.
We must go at once.
Haven't you had any sleep, Mr. Frodo?
I've gone and had too much.
Must be getting late.
No.
It isn't.
It isn't midday yet.
The days are growing darker.
Come on!
Must go! No time!
Not before Mr. Frodo's
had something to eat.
No time to lose, silly.
Here.
What about you?
Oh, no, I'm not hungry.
Leastways, not for lembas bread.
Sam.
All right.
We don't have that much left.
We have to be careful
or we're going to run out.
You go ahead and eat that, Mr. Frodo.
I've rationed it.
There should be enough.
For what?
The journey home.
Come, Hobbitses.
Very close now.
Very close to Mordor.
No safe places here.
Hurry.
It's good.
Definitely from the Shire.
Longbottom Leaf.
I feel like I'm back at
The Green Dragon.
Mmm. Green Dragon.
A mug of ale in my hand.
Putting my feet up on a settle
after a hard day's work.
Only, you've never done
a hard day's work.
Welcome, my lords...
to Isengard!
You young rascals!
A merry hunt you've led us on...
and now we find you feasting
and... and smoking!
We are sitting on a field of victory...
enjoying a few well-earned comforts.
The salted pork is particularly good.
Salted pork?
Huh. Hobbits.
We're under orders from Treebeard...
who's taken over management
of Isengard.
Young Master Gandalf.
I'm glad you've come.
Wood and water, stock and stone
I can master.
But there is a wizard to manage here...
locked in his tower.
Show yourself.
Be careful.
Even in defeat, Saruman is dangerous.
Well, let's just have his head
and be done with it.
No.
We need him alive.
We need him to talk.
You have fought many wars
and slain many men, Théoden King...
and made peace afterwards.
Can we not take counsel together
as we once did, my old friend?
Can we not have peace, you and I?
We shall have peace.
We shall have peace...
when you answer
for the burning of the Westfold...
and the children that lie dead there!
We shall have peace
when the lives of the soldiers...
whose bodies were hewn
even as they lay dead...
against the gates of the Hornburg,
are avenged!
When you hang from a gibbet
for the sport of your own crows...
we shall have peace.
Gibbets and crows?
Dotard!
What do you want, Gandalf Greyhame?
Let me guess. The Key of Orthanc.
Or perhaps the Keys of Barad-dûr itself...
along with the crowns of the seven kings
and the rods of the Five Wizards!
Your treachery has already cost
many lives.
Thousands more are now at risk.
But you could save them, Saruman.
You were deep in the enemy's counsel.
So you have come here for information.
I have some for you.
Something festers
in the heart of Middle-Earth.
Something that you have failed to see.
But the Great Eye has seen it.
Even now he presses his advantage.
His attack will come soon.
You're all going to die.
But you know this, don't you, Gandalf?
You cannot think that this Ranger
will ever sit upon the throne of Gondor.
This exile, crept from the shadows,
will never be crowned king.
Gandalf does not hesitate
to sacrifice those closest to him...
those he professes to love.
Tell me, what words of comfort
did you give the Halfling...
before you sent him to his doom?
The path that you have set him on
can only lead to death.
I've heard enough!
Shoot him.
Stick an arrow in his gob.
No.
Come down, Saruman...
and your life will be spared.
Save your pity and your mercy.
I have no use for it!
Saruman...
your staff is broken.
Grima, you need not follow him.
You were not always as you are now.
You were once a Man of Rohan.
Come down.
A Man of Rohan?
What is the house of Rohan...
but a thatched barn
where brigands drink in the reek...
and their brats roll on the floor
with the dogs?
The victory at Helm's Deep does not
belong to you, Théoden Horse-master.
You are a lesser son of greater sires.
Grima...
come down.
Be free of him.
Free? He will never be free.
No.
Get down, cur!
Saruman!
You were deep in the enemy's counsel.
Tell us what you know!
You withdraw your guard, and I will tell you
where your doom will be decided.
I will not be held prisoner here.
Send word to all our allies...
and to every corner of Middle-Earth
that still stands free.
The enemy moves against us.
We need to know where he will strike.
The filth of Saruman...
is washing away.
Trees will come back to live here.
Young trees.
Wild trees.
Pippin!
Bless my bark!
Peregrin Took!
I'll take that, my lad.
Quickly, now.
Hail the victorious dead.
Hail!
No pauses.
No spills.
And no regurgitation.
So it's a drinking game?
Last one standing wins.
What'll we drink to? Let's drink to victory!
To victory!
I am happy for you.
He is an honorable man.
You are both honorable men.
It was not Théoden of Rohan
who led our people to victory.
Ah, don't listen to me.
You are young.
And tonight is for you.
Here, here.
It's the Dwarves that go swimming
with little, hairy women.
I feel something.
A slight tingle in my fingers.
I think it's affecting me.
What did I say?
He can't hold his liquor.
Game over.
- ♪- ♪ Oh, you can search far and wide ♪
♪ You can drink the whole town dry ♪
♪ But you'll never find a beer so brown ♪
♪ As the one we drink in our hometown ♪
♪ You can drink your fancy ales ♪
♪ You can drink 'em by the flagon ♪
♪ But the only brew for the brave and true ♪
Pippin!
- ♪- ♪ But the only brew for the brave and true ♪
♪ Comes from The Green Dragon ♪
Thank you! I win!
No news of Frodo?
No word. Nothing.
We have time.
Every day, Frodo moves closer to Mordor.
Do we know that?
What does your heart tell you?
That Frodo is alive.
Yes.
Yes, he's alive.
Too risky. Too risky.
Thieves.
They stole it from us.
Kill them. Kill them. Kill them both.
Shh! Quiet! Mustn't wake them.
Mustn't ruin it now.
But they knows.
They knows.
They suspects us.
What's it saying, my precious, my love?
Is Sméagol losing his nerve?
No. Not.
Never. Sméagol hates nasty Hobbitses.
Sméagol wants to see them dead.
And we will.
Sméagol did it once.
He can do it again.
It's ours!
Ours!
We must get the precious.
We must get it back.
Patience! Patience, my love.
First we must lead them to her.
We lead them to the Winding Stair.
Yes, the stairs. And then?
Up, up, up, up,
up the stairs we go...
until we come to the tunnel.
And when they go in...
there's no coming out.
She's always hungry.
She always needs to feed.
She must eat.
All she gets is filthy Orcses.
And they doesn't taste very nice,
does they, precious?
No.
Not very nice at all, my love.
She hungers for sweeter meats.
Hobbit meat.
And when she throws away the bones
and the empty clothes...
then we will find it.
And take it for me!
For us.
Yes. We meant "for us."
Gollum. Gollum.
The precious will be ours...
once the Hobbitses are dead!
You treacherous little toad!
No! No! Master!
No, Sam! Leave him alone!
I heard it from his own mouth.
He means to murder us.
Never! Sméagol wouldn't hurt a fly.
He's a horrid, fat Hobbit...
who hates Sméagol...
and who makes up nasty lies.
You miserable little maggot!
I'll stove your head in!
Sam!
Call me a liar? You're a liar!
You scare him off, we're lost!
I don't care! I can't do it, Mr. Frodo.
I won't wait around for him to kill us!
I'm not sending him away.
You don't see it, do you?
He's a villain.
We can't do this by ourselves, Sam.
Not without a guide.
I need you on my side.
I'm on your side, Mr. Frodo.
I know, Sam. I know.
Trust me.
Come, Sméagol.
What time is it?
Not yet dawn.
I dreamed I saw a great wave...
climbing over green lands
and above the hills.
I stood upon the brink.
It was utterly dark in the abyss
before my feet.
A light shone behind me...
but I could not turn.
I could only stand there, waiting.
Night changes many thoughts.
Sleep...
while you can.
The stars are veiled.
Something stirs in the east.
A sleepless malice.
The Eye of the enemy is moving.
What are you doing?
Pippin!
Pippin?
Pippin.
What, are you mad?
I just want to look at it.
Just one more time.
Put it back.
Pippin.
No!
He is here.
I see you.
Pippin!
Help! Gandalf, help!
Someone help him!
Pippin!
Fool of a Took!
Look at me.
Gandalf, forgive me.
What did you see?
A tree.
There was a white tree...
in a courtyard of stone.
It was dead.
The city was burning.
Minas Tirith? Is that what you saw?
I saw...
I saw him.
I could hear his voice in my head.
And what did you tell him?
Speak!
He asked me my name.
I didn't answer.
He hurt me.
What did you tell him
about Frodo and the Ring?
There was no lie in Pippin's eyes.
A fool...
but an honest fool he remains.
He told Sauron nothing
of Frodo and the Ring.
We've been strangely fortunate.
Pippin saw in the palantir
a glimpse of the enemy's plan.
Sauron moves to strike
the city of Minas Tirith.
His defeat at Helm's Deep
showed our enemy one thing.
He knows the heir of Elendil
has come forth.
Men are not as weak as he supposed.
There is courage still, strength
enough perhaps to challenge him.
Sauron fears this.
He will not risk the peoples of
Middle-Earth uniting under one banner.
He will raze Minas Tirith
to the ground...
before he sees a king
return to the throne of Men.
If the beacons of Gondor are lit,
Rohan must be ready for war.
Tell me...
why should we ride to the aid
of those who did not come to ours?
What do we owe Gondor?
I will go.
No!
They must be warned.
They will be.
You must come to Minas Tirith
by another road.
Follow the river.
Look to the black ships.
Understand this:
Things are now in motion
that cannot be undone.
I ride for Minas Tirith...
and I won't be going alone.
Of all the inquisitive Hobbits,
Peregrin Took, you are the worst.
Hurry! Hurry!
Where are we going?
Why did you look?
Why do you always have to look?
I don't know. I can't help it.
You never can.
I'm sorry, all right?
I won't do it again.
Don't you understand?
The enemy thinks you have the Ring.
He's going to be looking for you, Pip.
They have to get you out of here.
And you...? You're coming with me?
Merry?
Come on.
How far is Minas Tirith?
Three days' ride, as the Nazgûl flies.
And you better hope we don't have
one of those on our tail.
Here.
Something for the road.
The last of the Longbottom Leaf.
I know you've run out.
You smoke too much, Pippin.
But... But we'll see each other soon.
Won't we?
I don't know.
I don't know what's going to happen.
Merry.
Run, Shadowfax.
Show us the meaning of haste.
Merry!
He's always followed me...
everywhere I went...
since before we were tweens.
I would get him into
the worst sort of trouble...
but I was always there to get him out.
Now he's gone.
Just like Frodo and Sam.
One thing I have learned about Hobbits:
They're a most hardy folk.
Foolhardy, maybe. He's a Took.
Take her by the safest road.
A ship lies anchored
in the Grey Havens.
It waits to carry her across the sea.
The last journey of Arwen Undómiel.
There is nothing for you here...
only death.
Lady Arwen...
we cannot delay.
Milady!
- Tell me what you have seen.
- Arwen.
You have the gift of foresight.
What did you see?
I looked into your future,
and I saw death.
But there is also life.
You saw there was a child.
You saw my son.
That future is almost gone.
But it is not lost.
Nothing is certain.
Some things are certain.
If I leave him now...
I will regret it forever.
It is time.
From the ashes a fire shall be woken
A light from the shadow shall spring
Renewed shall be blade that was broken
The crownless again shall be king
Re-forge the sword.
Your hands are cold.
The life of the Eldar is leaving you.
This was my choice.
Whether by your will or not...
there is no ship now
that can bear me hence.
We've just passed
into the realm of Gondor.
Minas Tirith.
City of kings.
Make way!
It's the tree.
Gandalf. Gandalf.
Yes, the White Tree of Gondor.
The tree of the king.
Lord Denethor, however,
is not king.
He is a steward only,
a caretaker of the throne.
Now listen carefully.
Lord Denethor is Boromir's father.
To give him news of his beloved son's
death would be most unwise.
And do not mention Frodo or the Ring.
And say nothing of Aragorn either.
In fact, it's better if you
don't speak at all, Peregrin Took.
Hail Denethor, son of Ecthelion,
lord and steward of Gondor.
I come with tidings in this dark hour,
and with counsel.
Perhaps you come to explain this.
Perhaps you come to tell me
why my son is dead.
Boromir died to save us...
my kinsman and me.
He fell defending us from many foes.
Pippin.
I offer you my service, such as it is...
in payment of this debt.
This is my first command to you.
How did you escape
and my son did not...
so mighty a man as he was?
The mightiest man
may be slain by one arrow...
and Boromir was pierced by many.
Get up.
My lord, there will be a time
to grieve for Boromir...
but it is not now.
War is coming.
The enemy is on your doorstep.
As steward, you are charged...
with the defense of this city.
Where are Gondor's armies?
You still have friends.
You are not alone in this fight.
Send word to Théoden of Rohan.
Light the beacons.
You think you are wise, Mithrandir.
Yet for all your subtleties,
you have not wisdom.
Do you think the eyes
of the White Tower are blind?
I have seen more than you know.
With your left hand you would use me
as a shield against Mordor.
And with your right
you'd seek to supplant me.
I know who rides with Théoden of Rohan.
Oh, yes. Word has reached my ears
of this Aragorn, son of Arathorn.
And I tell you now, I will not bow
to this Ranger from the North...
last of a ragged house
long bereft of lordship.
Authority is not given to you
to deny the return of the king, steward.
The rule of Gondor is mine
and no other's.
Come.
All has turned to vain ambition.
He would even use his grief
as a cloak.
A thousand years
this city has stood.
Now, at the whim of a madman,
it will fall.
And the White Tree,
the tree of the king...
will never bloom again.
Why are they still guarding it?
They guard it because they have hope.
A faint and fading hope
that one day it will flower.
That a king will come
and this city will be as it once was...
before it fell into decay.
The old wisdom borne out
of the West was forsaken.
Kings made tombs more splendid
than the houses of the living...
and counted the old names
of their descent...
dearer than the names of their sons.
Childless lords sat in aged halls,
musing on heraldry...
or in high, cold towers,
asking questions of the stars.
And so the people of Gondor
fell into ruin.
The line of kings failed.
The White Tree withered.
The rule of Gondor was given over
to lesser men.
Mordor.
Yes, there it lies.
This city has dwelt ever
in the sight of its shadow.
A storm is coming.
This is not the weather of the world.
This is a device of Sauron's making.
A broil of fume
he sends ahead of his host.
The Orcs of Mordor
have no love of daylight...
so he covers the face of the sun...
to ease their passage
along the road to war.
When the Shadow of Mordor
reaches this city...
it will begin.
Well...
Minas Tirith...
So where are we off to next?
Oh, it's too late for that, Peregrin.
There's no leaving this city.
Help must come to us.
It must be getting near teatime.
Leastways, it would be in decent places
where there is still teatime.
We're not in decent places.
Mr. Frodo?
What is it?
It's just a feeling.
I don't think I'll be coming back.
Yes, you will. Of course you will.
That's just morbid thinking.
We're going there and back again...
just like Mr. Bilbo.
You'll see.
I think these lands
were once part of the kingdom of Gondor.
Long ago, when there was a king.
Mr. Frodo, look.
The king has got a crown again.
Come on, Hobbits!
Mustn't stop now. This way.
So I imagine this is just
a ceremonial position.
I mean, they don't actually expect me
to do any fighting.
Do they?
You're in the service of the steward now.
You'll have to do as you're told,
Peregrin Took.
Ridiculous Hobbit.
Guard of the Citadel.
Thank you.
There's no more stars.
Is it time?
Yes.
It's so quiet.
It's the deep breath before the plunge.
I don't want to be in a battle...
but waiting on the edge of one
I can't escape is even worse.
Is there any hope, Gandalf,
for Frodo and Sam?
There never was much hope.
Just a fool's hope.
Our enemy is ready.
His full strength's gathered.
Not only Orcs, but Men as well.
Legions of Haradrim from the south...
mercenaries from the coast.
All will answer Mordor's call.
Come on.
This will be the end of Gondor
as we know it.
Here the hammer stroke will fall hardest.
If the river is taken,
if the garrison at Osgiliath falls...
the last defense of this city
will be gone.
But we have the White Wizard.
That's got to count for something.
Gandalf?
Sauron has yet to reveal
his deadliest servant...
the one who will lead
Mordor's armies in war.
The one they say no living man can kill.
The Witch-king of Angmar.
You've met him before.
He stabbed Frodo on Weathertop.
He is the lord of the Nazgûl...
the greatest of the Nine.
Minas Morgul is his lair.
The Dead City.
Very nasty place. Full of enemies.
Quick. Quick.
They will see. They will see.
Come away. Come away.
Look, we have found it.
The way into Mordor.
The secret stair.
Climb.
No, Mr. Frodo!
Not that way!
What's it doing?
No.
- They're calling me.
- No.
Hide! Hide!
I can feel his blade.
We come to it at last.
The great battle of our time.
Come away, Hobbits.
We climb. We must climb.
The board is set.
The pieces are moving.
Up, up, up the stairs we go.
And then it's into the tunnel.
Hey, what's in this tunnel?
You listen to me,
and you listen good and proper.
Anything happens to him,
you have me to answer to.
One sniff something's not right...
one hair stands up
on the back of my head, it's over.
No more slinker. No more stinker.
You're gone. Got it?
I'm watching you.
What was that about?
Nothing. Just clearing something up.
Peregrin Took, my lad,
there is a task now to be done.
Another opportunity for one
of the Shire-folk to prove their great worth.
You must not fail me.
It's been very quiet across the river.
The Orcs are lying low.
The garrison may have moved out.
We've sent scouts to Cair Andros.
If the Orcs attack from the north,
we'll have some warning.
Quiet.
We need 10 more.
Kill him!
They're not coming from the north.
To the river. Quick. Quick.
Go. Come on.
Faster.
Draw swords.
Hold! Hold them!
What?
Amon Dîn.
The beacon.
The beacon of Amon Dîn is lit.
Hope is kindled.
The beacons of Minas Tirith!
The beacons are lit!
Gondor calls for aid.
And Rohan will answer.
Muster the Rohirrim.
Assemble the army at Dunharrow.
As many men as can be found.
You have two days.
On the third,
we ride for Gondor and war.
- Forward.
- Very good, sir.
Gamling.
My lord.
Make haste
across the Riddermark.
Summon every able-bodied man
to Dunharrow.
I will.
Will you ride with us?
Just to the encampment.
It's tradition for the women
of the court to farewell the men.
The men have found their captain.
They will follow you into battle,
even to death.
You have given us hope.
Excuse me.
I have a sword.
Please accept it.
I offer you my service, Théoden King.
And gladly I accept it.
You shall be Meriadoc,
esquire of Rohan.
Horse-Men.
I wish I could muster a legion of Dwarves,
fully armed and filthy.
Your kinsmen may have no need
to ride to war.
I fear war already marches
on their own lands.
The doom of our time will be decided.
Now is the hour.
Riders of Rohan, oaths you have taken.
Now, fulfill them all.
To lord and land! Hyah!
Faramir!
We can't hold them. The city is lost.
Tell the men to break cover.
We ride for Minas Tirith.
Nazgûl.
Take cover!
Nazgûl!
Fall back. Fall back to Minas Tirith!
Fall back!
- Retreat! Retreat!
- Run for your lives!
The age of Men is over.
The time of the Orc has come.
- Keep going.
- It's the Nazgûl.
Take cover, my lord!
It's coming!
It's Mithrandir.
The White Rider!
Pull!
Mithrandir.
They broke through our defenses.
They've taken the bridge
and the west bank.
Battalions of Orcs are crossing the river.
It is as the Lord Denethor predicted.
Long has he foreseen this doom.
Foreseen and done nothing.
Faramir?
This is not the first Halfling
to have crossed your path.
No.
You've seen Frodo and Sam?
Where? When?
In Ithilien.
Not two days ago.
Gandalf, they're taking the road
to the Morgul Vale.
And then the pass of Cirith Ungol.
What does that mean?
What's wrong?
Faramir, tell me everything.
Tell me all you know.
This is how you would serve your city?
You would risk its utter ruin?
I did what I judged to be right.
What you judged to be right.
You sent the Ring of Power into Mordor
in the hands of a witless Halfling.
It should have been brought back
to the Citadel to be kept safe.
Hidden.
Dark and deep in the vaults...
not to be used.
Unless at the uttermost end of need.
I would not use the Ring.
Not if Minas Tirith were falling in ruin
and I alone could save her.
Ever you desire to appear lordly
and gracious...
as a king of old.
Boromir would have remembered
his father's need.
He would have brought me a kingly gift.
Boromir would not
have brought the Ring.
He would have stretched out his hand to
this thing and taken it. He would've fallen.
You know nothing of this matter!
He would have kept it for his own.
And when he returned...
you would not have known your son.
Boromir was loyal to me!
Not some wizard's pupil!
Father?
My son.
Leave me.
Careful, master. Careful.
Very far to fall.
Very dangerous are the stairs.
Come, master.
Come to Sméagol.
Mr. Frodo.
Get back, you!
Don't touch him!
Why does he hates poor Sméagol?
What has Sméagol ever done to him?
Master?
Master carries heavy burden.
Sméagol knows.
Heavy, heavy burden.
Fat one cannot know.
Sméagol look after master.
He wants it.
He needs it.
Sméagol sees it in his eye.
Very soon he will ask you for it.
You will see.
The fat one will take it from you.
Send forth all legions.
Do not stop the attack
until the city is taken.
Slay them all.
What of the wizard?
I will break him.
Where are Théoden's riders?
Will Rohan's army come?
Mithrandir.
Courage is the best defense
that you have now.
What were you thinking, Peregrin Took?
What service can a Hobbit
offer such a great lord of Men?
It was well-done.
A generous deed should not
be checked with cold counsel.
You are to join the tower guard.
I didn't think they would find any livery
that would fit me.
Once belonged to a young boy
of the city.
A very foolish one...
who wasted many hours slaying dragons
instead of attending to his studies.
This was yours?
Yes, it was mine.
My father had it made for me.
Well...
I'm taller than you were then.
Though I'm not likely to grow anymore,
except sideways.
Never fitted me either.
Boromir was always the soldier.
They were so alike, he and my father.
Proud.
Stubborn even.
But strong.
I think you have strength
of a different kind.
And one day your father will see it.
Here do I swear fealty
and service to Gondor...
in living or dying...
from...
From this hour henceforth...
until my lord release me...
or death take me.
And I shall not forget it...
nor fail to reward
that which is given.
Fealty with love.
Valor with honor.
Disloyalty with vengeance.
I do not think we should so lightly
abandon the outer defenses...
defenses that your brother
long held intact.
What would you have me do?
I will not yield...
the river in Pelennor unfought.
Osgiliath must be retaken.
My lord, Osgiliath is overrun.
Much must be risked in war.
Is there a captain here who still has
the courage to do his lord's will?
You wish now that our places
had been exchanged...
that I had died
and Boromir had lived.
Yes.
I wish that.
Since you were robbed
of Boromir...
I will do what I can
in his stead.
If I should return,
think better of me, Father.
That will depend on the manner
of your return.
Ugh.
What are you up to?
Sneaking off, are we?
Sneaking?
Fat Hobbit is always so polite.
Sméagol shows them secret ways
that nobody else could find...
and they say "sneak."
Sneak?
Very nice friend.
Oh, yes, my precious.
Very nice, very nice.
All right. All right!
You just startled me is all.
What were you doing?
Sneaking.
Fine. Have it your own way.
I'm sorry to wake you, Mr. Frodo.
We have to be moving on.
It's dark still.
It's always dark here.
It's gone!
The Elven bread.
What?
That's all we have left.
He took it. He must have!
Sméagol?
No, no, not poor Sméagol.
Sméagol hates nasty Elf bread.
You're a lying rat!
What did you do with it?!
He doesn't eat it.
- He can't have taken it.
- Look.
What's this?
Crumbs on his jacketses.
He took it!
He took it.
I seen him. He's always stuffing
his face when master's not looking.
That's a filthy lie!
You stinking, two-faced sneak!
- Sam!
- Call me...
Stop it!
Sam!
I'll kill him!
Sam! No!
Oh, my... I'm sorry. I didn't mean it
to go so far. I was just so... So angry.
Here, just...
Let's just rest a bit.
I'm all right.
No.
No, you're not all right.
You're exhausted.
It's that Gollum.
It's this place.
It's that thing around your neck.
I could help a bit.
I could carry it for a while.
Carry it for a while.
I could carry it... I could carry it.
Share the load... Share the load...
the load... the load.
Get away!
I don't want to keep it.
I just want to help.
See? See?
He wants it for himself.
Shut up, you!
Go away!
Get out of here!
No, Sam.
It's you.
I'm sorry, Sam.
But he's a liar.
He's poisoned you against me.
You can't help me anymore.
You don't mean that.
Go home.
Faramir!
Your father's will has turned
to madness.
Do not throw away your life
so rashly.
Where does my allegiance lie
if not here?
This is the city of the Men of Númenor.
I will gladly give my life
to defend her beauty...
her memory, her wisdom.
Your father loves you, Faramir.
He will remember it
before the end.
Can you sing, Master Hobbit?
Well...
yes.
At least, well enough
for my own people.
But we have no songs
for great halls...
and evil times.
And why should your songs
be unfit for my halls?
Come, sing me a song.
♪ Home is behind ♪
♪ The world ahead ♪
♪ And there are many paths to tread ♪
♪ Through shadow ♪
♪ To the edge of night ♪
♪ Until the stars are all alight ♪
♪ Mist and shadow ♪
♪ Cloud and shade ♪
♪ All shall fade ♪
♪ All shall ♪
♪ Fade ♪
March! March!
March! March! March!
Make way for the king.
Make way.
The king is here.
My lord.
Hail to you, sire.
Grimbold, how many?
I bring 500 men from the Westfold,
my lord.
We have 300 more
from Fenmarch, Théoden King.
Where are the riders from Snowbourn?
None have come, my lord.
Less than half of what I'd hoped for.
Six thousand will not be enough
to break the lines of Mordor.
More will come.
Every hour lost hastens Gondor's defeat.
We have till dawn,
then we must ride.
The horses are restless...
and the men are quiet.
They grow nervous in the shadow
of the mountain.
That road there...
where does that lead?
It is the road to the Dimholt,
the door under the mountain.
None who venture there ever return.
That mountain is evil.
Hold!
Aragorn.
Let's find some food.
There.
A true esquire of Rohan.
I'm ready.
Sorry.
It isn't all that dangerous.
It's not even sharp.
Well, that's no good. You won't kill
many Orcs with a blunt blade.
Come on.
To the smithy. Go!
You should not encourage him.
You should not doubt him.
I do not doubt his heart,
only the reach of his arm.
Why should Merry be left behind?
He has as much cause
to go to war as you.
Why can he not fight
for those he loves?
You know as little of war
as that Hobbit.
When the fear takes him...
and the blood and the screams
and the horror of battle take hold...
do you think he would stand and fight?
He would flee.
And he would be right to do so.
I choose a mortal life.
I wish I could've seen him...
one last time.
Sir?
King Théoden awaits you, my lord.
I take my leave.
My lord Elrond.
I come on behalf of one whom I love.
Arwen is dying.
She will not long survive the evil
that now spreads from Mordor.
The light of the Evenstar is failing.
As Sauron's power grows,
her strength wanes.
Arwen's life is now tied
to the fate of the Ring.
The Shadow is upon us, Aragorn.
The end has come.
It will not be our end, but his.
You ride to war, but not to victory.
Sauron's armies march on Minas Tirith,
this you know.
But in secret he sends another force
which will attack from the river.
A fleet of Corsair ships sails
from the south.
They'll be in the city in two days.
You're outnumbered, Aragorn.
You need more men.
There are none.
There are those who dwell
in the mountain.
Murderers...
traitors.
You would call upon them to fight?
They believe in nothing.
They answer to no one.
They will answer
to the king of Gondor.
Andúril, the Flame of the West,
forged from the shards of Narsil.
Sauron will not have forgotten
the Sword of Elendil.
The blade that was broken
shall return to Minas Tirith.
The man who can wield
the power of this sword...
can summon to him an army more
deadly than any that walks this Earth.
Put aside the Ranger.
Become who you were born to be.
Take the Dimholt road.
Why are you doing this?
The war lies to the east.
You cannot leave on the eve of battle.
You cannot abandon the men.
We need you here.
Why have you come?
Do you not know?
It is but a shadow and a thought
that you love.
I cannot give you what you seek.
I have wished you joy
since first I saw you.
Just where do you think you're off to?
Not this time.
This time you must stay, Gimli.
Mm.
Have you learned nothing
of the stubbornness of Dwarves?
You might as well accept it.
We're going with you, laddie.
What's happening?
Where is he going?
Where's he going?
I don't understand.
Lord Aragorn!
Why does he leave on the eve of battle?
He leaves because there is no hope.
He leaves because he must.
Too few have come.
We cannot defeat
the armies of Mordor.
No...
we cannot.
But we will meet them
in battle nonetheless.
I have left instruction.
The people are to follow
your rule in my stead.
Take up my seat in the Golden Hall.
Long may you defend Edoras...
if the battle goes ill.
What other duty would you
have me do, my lord?
Duty?
No.
I would have you smile again...
not grieve for those
whose time has come.
You shall live to see
these days renewed...
and no more despair.
What kind of army would linger
in such a place?
One that is cursed.
Long ago, the Men of the Mountains
swore an oath...
to the last king of Gondor...
to come to his aid...
to fight.
But when the time came...
when Gondor's need was dire...
they fled...
vanishing into the darkness
of the mountain.
And so Isildur cursed them...
never to rest until they had
fulfilled their pledge.
Who shall call them
from the Grey twilight?
The forgotten people.
The heir of him to whom
the oath they swore.
From the north shall he come.
Need shall drive him.
He shall pass the door
to the Paths of the Dead.
The very warmth of my blood
seems stolen away.
The way is shut.
It was made by those
who are dead.
And the Dead keep it.
The way is shut.
Brego!
I do not fear death.
Well, this is a thing unheard-of.
An Elf will go underground
where a Dwarf dare not?
Oh.
Oh, I'd never hear the end of it.
We must ride light and swift.
It is a long road ahead.
And man and beast must reach the end
with the strength to fight.
Little Hobbits do not belong in war,
Master Meriadoc.
All my friends have gone to battle.
I would be ashamed to be left behind.
It is a three-day gallop to Minas Tirith.
And none of my riders can bear you
as a burden.
I want to fight.
I will say no more.
Ride with me.
Milady.
Form up! Move out!
Ride now to Gondor!
What is it?
What do you see?
I see shapes of men.
And of horses.
Where?
Pale banners like shreds of cloud.
Spears rise...
like winter-thickets
through a shroud of mist.
The Dead are following.
They have been summoned.
The Dead?
Summoned?
I knew that.
Huh. Ha.
Very good.
Very good! Legolas!
Do not look down.
Who enters my domain?
One who will have your allegiance.
The Dead do not suffer the living to pass.
You will suffer me.
The way is shut.
It was made by those who are dead.
And the Dead keep it.
The way is shut.
Now you must die.
I summon you to fulfill your oath.
None but the king of Gondor
may command me.
That line was broken.
It has been remade.
Fight for us...
and regain your honor.
What say you?
Ah! You waste your time, Aragorn.
They had no honor in life,
they have none now in death.
I am Isildur's heir.
Fight for me...
and I will hold your oaths fulfilled.
What say you?
You have my word!
Fight, and I will release you
from this living death!
What say you?!
Stand, you traitors!
Out!
Legolas!
Run!
We fight.
Open the gate! Quick!
Quick! Hurry!
Faramir!
Say not that he has fallen.
They were outnumbered.
None survived.
Fear.
The city is rank with it.
Let us ease their pain.
Release the prisoners.
Catapults!
Shields up!
My sons are spent.
My line has ended.
He's alive!
The House of Stewards has failed.
He needs medicine, my lord.
My line has ended!
My lord!
Put it in!
Rohan...
has deserted us.
Théoden's betrayed me.
Abandon your posts!
Flee! Flee for your lives!
Oh!
Prepare for battle!
Hurry, men! To the wall! Defend the wall!
Over here!
Return to your posts!
Send these foul beasts into the abyss.
Stay where you are.
We need more rubble!
Watch out!
Down to the lower levels. Quick!
Double up, men!
Yah!
Hold them back! Do not give in to fear.
Stand to your posts! Fight!
Not at the towers!
Aim for the trolls! Kill the trolls!
Bring them down!
Fight them back!
Peregrin Took!
Go back to the Citadel!
They'd called us out to fight.
This is no place for a Hobbit.
Guard of the Citadel, indeed.
Now, back, up the hill. Quickly. Quick!
What are you doing,
you useless scum?!
The door won't give. It's too strong.
Get back there and smash it down.
But nothing can breach it.
Grond will breach it.
Bring up the wolf's head.
Grond! Grond! Grond! Grond!
Grond! Grond! Grond!
You may go no further.
You will not enter Gondor.
Who are you to deny us passage?
Legolas, fire a warning shot
past the bosun's ear.
Mind your aim.
Oh!
That's it. Right. We warned you.
Prepare to be boarded.
Boarded?
By you and whose army?
This army.
In there.
What is this place?
Master must go inside the tunnel.
Now that I'm here, I don't think I want to.
It's the only way.
Go in...
or go back.
I can't go back.
- What's that smell?
- Orcses' filth.
Orcses come in here sometimes.
Hurry.
This way.
Sméagol?
Over here.
Oh!
Aah! Aah!
It's sticky. What is it?
You'll see.
Oh, yes.
You will see.
Sméagol?
Sméagol!
Sam.
And you, Frodo Baggins...
I give you the light of Eärendil,
our most beloved star.
May it be a light for you
in dark places...
when all other lights go out.
Naughty little fly
Why does he cry?
Caught in a web
Soon you'll be...
Eaten.
Got away, did it, precious?
Not this time.
Not this time!
No!
It wasn't us. It wasn't us!
Sméagol wouldn't hurt master.
We promised.
You must believe us.
It was the precious.
The precious made us do it.
I have to destroy it, Sméagol.
I have to destroy it for both our sakes.
No!
I'm so sorry, Sam.
I'm so sorry.
This task was appointed
to you, Frodo of the Shire.
If you do not find a way...
no one will.
The lower level's in flames.
Everywhere,
legions of the enemy advance.
Time is against us.
Make ready!
Take heart, Merry.
It will soon be over.
My lady...
you are fair and brave...
and have much to live for...
and many who love you.
I know it is too late to turn aside.
I know there is not much point
now in hoping.
If I were a knight of Rohan,
capable of great deeds...
But I'm not.
I'm a Hobbit.
And I know I can't save Middle-Earth.
I just want to help my friends.
Frodo.
Sam.
Pippin.
More than anything,
I wish I could see them again.
Make haste.
We ride through the night.
To battle.
Back to the gate!
Hurry!
I am steward of the House of Anárion.
Thus have I walked.
And thus now will I sleep.
Gondor is lost.
There is no hope for Men.
Why do the fools fly?
Better to die sooner than late.
For die we must.
No tomb for Denethor
and Faramir.
No long, slow sleep of death embalmed.
We shall burn,
like the heathen kings of old.
Bring wood and oil.
Steady.
You are soldiers of Gondor.
No matter what comes through that gate,
you will stand your ground.
Run!
Volley!
Fire!
Let him go, you filth.
Let him go!
You will not touch him again.
Come on and finish it.
Ha! Back!
Mr. Frodo.
Oh, no.
Frodo.
Mr. Frodo.
Wake up.
Don't leave me here alone.
Don't go where I can't follow.
Wake up.
Not asleep.
Dead.
You get back, you scum!
What's this?
Looks like old Shelob's
been having a bit of fun.
Killed another one, has she?
No.
This fellow ain't dead.
Not dead?
She jabs him with her stinger,
and he goes as limp as a boned fish.
Then she has her way with them.
That's how she likes to feed.
Fresh blood.
Get him to the tower!
Samwise, you fool.
This scum will be awake
in a couple of hours.
Then he'll wish he'd never been born.
The house of his spirit crumbles.
He is burning.
Already burning.
He's not dead.
He's not dead!
No! No!
- Farewell, Peregrin, son of Paladin.
- No! No! No!
I release you from my service.
Go now and die in what way
seems best to you.
Pour oil on the wood!
Come on, soldier! Move it!
Hurry along there! Hurry along!
Gandalf!
Where is Gandalf?
Retreat!
The city is breached!
Fall back to the second level!
Get the women and children out!
Get them out!
Retreat!
Come on. Come on.
Move into the city. Kill all in your path.
Take them down!
Fight. Fight to the last man!
Fight for your lives!
Gandalf!
Denethor has lost his mind!
He's burning Faramir alive!
Up! Quickly!
Go back to the abyss.
Fall into the nothingness
that awaits you and your master.
Do you not know death
when you see it, old man?
This is my hour.
Gandalf!
You have failed.
The world of Men will fall.
Courage, Merry.
Courage for our friends.
Form ranks, you maggots. Form ranks!
Pikes in front. Archers behind.
Grimbold, take your company right
after you pass the wall.
Forth, and fear no darkness!
Arise, arise, Riders of Théoden!
Spears shall be shaken,
shields shall be splintered...
a sword-day, a red day...
ere the sun rises!
Whatever happens, stay with me.
I'll look after you.
Ride now!
Ride! Ride for ruin...
and the world's ending!
Death!
Forth Eorlingas!
Fire!
Death!
Charge!
Fire at will!
Set a fire in our flesh.
Stay this madness!
You may triumph in the field of battle
for a day...
but against the power that has risen
in the east...
there is no victory.
No!
You will not take my son from me!
No! No!
Yah!
Faramir.
So passes Denethor, son of Ecthelion.
Drive them to the river!
Make safe the city!
Re-form the line!
Sound the charge! Take them head-on!
Charge!
Cut him down!
Follow me!
Take the reins. Pull him left!
Left!
Aim for their heads!
Bring it down! Bring it down!
Bring it down!
Merry!
I didn't think it would end this way.
End?
No, the journey doesn't end here.
Death is just another path...
one that we all must take.
The Grey rain curtain
of this world rolls back...
and all turns to silver glass.
And then you see it.
What, Gandalf?
See what?
White shores...
and beyond.
A far green country...
under a swift sunrise.
Well...
that isn't so bad.
No.
No, it isn't.
Rally to me! To me!
Feast on his flesh.
I will kill you if you touch him.
Do not come between
the Nazgûl and his prey.
Late as usual, pirate scum!
There's knife-work here needs doing.
Come on, you sea rats!
Get off your ships!
There's plenty for the both of us.
May the best Dwarf win.
You fool.
No man can kill me.
Die now.
I am no man.
- Fifteen! Sixteen!
- Seventeen!
Merry!
Legolas!
Thirty-three, thirty-four.
That still only counts as one!
Come on, then. Come on!
My eyes darken.
No.
I am going to save you.
You already did.
My body is broken.
You have to let me go.
I go to my fathers...
in whose mighty company...
I shall not now feel ashamed.
Release us.
Bad idea.
Very handy in a tight spot, these lads,
despite the fact they're dead.
You gave us your word.
I hold your oath fulfilled.
Go.
Be at peace.
Merry.
No!
Merry!
Merry.
Merry, it's me.
It's Pippin.
I knew you'd find me.
Yes.
Are you going to leave me?
No, Merry.
I'm going to look after you.
Hands off!
That shiny shirt, that's mine.
It's going to the Great Eye,
along with everything else.
I don't take orders from
stinking Morgul-rats!
You touch it, and I'll stick
this blade in your gut.
The scum tried to knife me.
Kill him!
That's for Frodo!
And for the Shire!
And that's for my old Gaffer!
Stop your squealing, you dunghill rat.
I'm gonna bleed you like a stuck pig.
Not if I stick you first.
Sam!
Oh, Sam, I'm so sorry.
Sorry for everything.
Let's get you out of here.
It's too late. It's over.
They've taken it. Sam...
they took the Ring.
Begging your pardon, but they haven't.
I thought I'd lost you.
So I took it.
Only for safekeeping.
Give it to me.
Give me the Ring, Sam.
Sam.
Give me the Ring.
You must understand.
The Ring is my burden.
It will destroy you, Sam.
Come on, Mr. Frodo.
We best find you some clothes.
You can't go walking through Mordor
in naught but your skin.
We did it, Mr. Frodo.
We made it to Mordor.
There are so many of them.
We'll never get through unseen.
It's him, the Eye.
We have to go in there, Mr. Frodo.
There's nothing for it.
Come on. Let's just make it
down the hill for starters.
Frodo has passed beyond my sight.
The darkness is deepening.
If Sauron had the Ring,
we would know it.
It's only a matter of time.
He has suffered a defeat, yes...
but behind the walls of Mordor,
our enemy is regrouping.
Let him stay there.
Let him rot! Why should we care?
Because 10,000 Orcs now stand
between Frodo and Mount Doom.
I've sent him to his death.
No.
There is still hope for Frodo.
He needs time and safe passage
across the plains of Gorgoroth.
We can give him that.
How?
Draw out Sauron's armies.
Empty his lands.
Then we gather our full strength
and march on the Black Gate.
We cannot achieve victory
through strength of arms.
Not for ourselves.
But we can give Frodo his chance
if we keep Sauron's Eye fixed upon us.
Keep him blind to all else that moves.
A diversion.
Certainty of death...
small chance of success...
what are we waiting for?
Sauron will suspect a trap.
He will not take the bait.
Oh, I think he will.
Long have you hunted me.
Long have I eluded you.
No more.
Behold the Sword of Elendil.
There is no warmth left in the sun.
It grows so cold.
It's just the damp
of the first spring rain.
I do not believe this darkness
will endure.
Look, the Orcs...
they're moving off.
You see, Mr. Frodo...
some luck at last.
Move it, you slugs!
Come on! Faster!
Come along, you scum...
I'll whip you down to the bone, you...
Come on!
What have I told you?!
Get up!
Come on, you slugs!
You two are going straight
to the front line!
Now, move it! Go on!
Fall in! Move it!
To the Gate, you slugs!
Now, move it!
Don't you know we're at war?
Company, halt!
Inspection!
Sam, help me.
Mr. Frodo!
Stand up, Mr. Frodo.
Stand up!
It's so heavy.
Oh, no.
What do I do?
What do we do?
- Hit me.
- What?
Hit me, Sam. Start fighting.
Get off of me!
Nobody pushes me, you filthy maggot.
Break it up! Break it up!
Oi! I'll have your guts if you don't
shut this rabble down!
Go, Sam. Now!
Move along, scum!
Back in the line!
You maggots!
Get back into the line,
you slugs!
Dig it, you slugs. Move it.
Move it!
I can't...
I can't manage the Ring, Sam.
It's... It's...
It's such a weight to carry.
It...
Such a weight.
We're going that way.
Straight as we can.
There's no point carrying anything
we're not sure to need.
Mr. Frodo.
Look.
There is light...
and beauty up there...
that no shadow can touch.
Take mine.
There's a few drops left.
There will be none left
for the return journey.
I don't think there will be
a return journey, Mr. Frodo.
Frodo, get down!
Hide!
Frodo!
Where are they?
Let the Lord of the Black Land come forth!
Let justice be done upon him!
My master, Sauron the Great,
bids thee welcome.
Is there any in this rout
with authority to treat with me?
We do not come to treat with Sauron...
faithless and accursed.
Tell your master this:
The armies of Mordor must disband.
He is to depart these lands,
never to return.
Aha. Old Greybeard.
I have a token I was bidden
to show thee.
Frodo.
Silence.
No!
Silence!
The Halfling was dear to thee, I see.
Know that he suffered greatly
at the hands of his host.
Who would've thought one so small
could endure so much pain?
And he did, Gandalf.
He did.
And who is this?
Isildur's heir?
It takes more to make a king
than a broken Elvish blade.
I guess that concludes negotiations.
I do not believe it.
I will not.
Pull back.
Pull back!
It's gone, Mr. Frodo.
The light's passed on,
away towards the north.
Something's drawn its gaze.
Hold your ground! Hold your ground.
Sons of Gondor, of Rohan, my brothers!
I see in your eyes...
the same fear that would take
the heart of me.
A day may come
when the courage of Men fails...
when we forsake our friends
and break all bonds of fellowship.
But it is not this day.
An hour of wolves
and shattered shields...
when the age of Men
comes crashing down.
But it is not this day.
This day we fight!
By all that you hold dear
on this good Earth...
I bid you stand, Men of the West!
Never thought I'd die fighting
side by side with an Elf.
What about side by side with a friend?
Aye.
I could do that.
Do you remember the Shire,
Mr. Frodo?
It'll be spring soon.
And the orchards will be in blossom.
And the birds will be nesting
in the hazel thicket.
And they'll be sowing
the summer barley in the lower fields...
and eating the first
of the strawberries with cream.
Do you remember
the taste of strawberries?
No, Sam.
I can't recall the taste of food...
nor the sound of water...
nor the touch of grass.
I'm...
naked in the dark.
There's... There's nothing.
No veil between me
and the wheel of fire.
I can see him...
with my waking eyes.
Then let us be rid of it...
once and for all.
Come on, Mr. Frodo.
I can't carry it for you...
but I can carry you.
Come on!
Aragorn.
Elessar.
For Frodo.
Look, Mr. Frodo.
A doorway.
We're almost there.
Clever Hobbits to climb so high!
Mustn't go that way.
Mustn't hurt the precious.
You swore!
You swore on the precious!
Sméagol promised!
Sméagol lied.
Frodo!
Eagles.
The eagles are coming!
Frodo!
I'm here, Sam.
Destroy it!
Go on! Now!
Throw it in the fire!
What are you waiting for?
Just let it go!
The Ring is mine.
No.
No!
Yes!
Precious! Precious!
Give me your hand!
Take my hand!
No!
Don't you let go.
Don't let go.
Reach!
Frodo!
It's gone.
It's done.
Yes, Mr. Frodo.
It's over now.
I can see the Shire.
The Brandywine River.
Bag End.
Gandalf's fireworks.
The lights in the Party Tree.
Rosie Cotton dancing.
She had ribbons in her hair.
If ever I was to marry someone...
it would've been her.
It would've been her.
I'm glad to be with you,
Samwise Gamgee...
here at the end of all things.
Gandalf?
Frodo!
Gimli!
Now come the days of the king.
May they be blessed.
This day does not belong to one man...
but to all.
Let us together rebuild this world...
that we may share
in the days of peace.
My friends...
you bow to no one.
And thus it was.
A Fourth Age of Middle-Earth began.
And the Fellowship of the Ring...
though eternally bound
by friendship and love...
was ended.
Thirteen months to the day since Gandalf
sent us on our long journey...
we found ourselves
looking upon a familiar sight.
We were home.
Hi.
Hey, watch the pumpkin.
Hey!
More of the same, Rosie.
Good night, lads.
Hm?
How do you pick up the threads
of an old life?
How do you go on...
when in your heart
you begin to understand...
there is no going back?
There are some things
that time cannot mend...
some hurts that go too deep...
that have taken hold.
Mr. Frodo?
What is it?
It's been four years to the day
since Weathertop, Sam.
It's never really healed.
"There and Back Again: A Hobbit's Tale
by Bilbo Baggins.
And The Lord of the Rings
by Frodo Baggins."
You finished it.
Not quite.
There's room for a little more.
Bilbo once told me his part
in this tale would end...
that each of us must come and go
in the telling.
Bilbo's story was now over.
There would be no more journeys
for him...
save one.
Tell me again, lad, where are we going?
To the harbor, Bilbo.
The Elves have accorded you
a special honor...
a place on the last ship
to leave Middle-Earth.
Frodo...
any chance of seeing
that old Ring of mine again?
The one I gave you.
I'm sorry, Uncle.
I'm afraid I lost it.
Oh.
Pity.
I should like to have held it
one last time.
Oh!
Well, here's a sight
I have never seen before.
The power of the Three Rings is ended.
The time has come...
for the dominion of Men.
I think I'm...
quite ready
for another adventure.
Farewell...
my brave Hobbits.
My work is now finished.
Here at last,
on the shores of the sea...
comes the end of our Fellowship.
I will not say, "Do not weep"...
for not all tears are an evil.
It is time, Frodo.
What does he mean?
We set out to save the Shire, Sam.
And it has been saved.
But not for me.
You don't mean that.
You can't leave.
The last pages are for you, Sam.
My dear Sam:
You cannot always be torn in two.
You will have to be one and whole
for many years.
You have so much to enjoy
and to be and to do.
Your part in the story will go on.
Well...
I'm back.
♪ Lay down ♪
♪ Your sweet and weary head ♪
♪ Night is falling ♪
♪ You have come To journey's end ♪
♪ Sleep now ♪
♪ And dream ♪
♪ Of the ones who came before ♪
♪ They are calling ♪
♪ From across The distant shore ♪
♪ Why do you weep? ♪
♪ What are these tears ♪
♪ Upon your face? ♪
♪ Soon you will see ♪
♪ All of your fears Will pass away ♪
♪ Safe in my arms ♪
♪ You're only sleeping ♪
♪ What can you see ♪
♪ On the horizon? ♪
♪ Why do the white gulls ♪
♪ Call? ♪
♪ Across the sea ♪
♪ A pale moon rises ♪
♪ The ships have come ♪
♪ To carry you home ♪
♪ And all will turn ♪
♪ To silver glass ♪
♪ A light on the water ♪
♪ All souls pass ♪
♪ Hope fades ♪
♪ Into the world of night ♪
♪ Through shadows falling ♪
♪ Out of memory and time ♪
♪ Don't say ♪
♪ We have come now to the end ♪
♪ White shores are calling ♪
♪ You and I will meet again ♪
♪ And you'll be here In my arms ♪
♪ Just sleeping ♪
♪ What can you see ♪
♪ On the horizon? ♪
♪ Why do the white gulls ♪
♪ Call? ♪
♪ Across the sea ♪
♪ A pale moon rises ♪
♪ The ships have come ♪
♪ To carry you home ♪
♪ And all will turn ♪
♪ To silver glass ♪
♪ A light on the water ♪
♪ Grey ships pass ♪
♪ Into the West ♪